A Guide to the Library of Virginia, Capitol Model Project Records, 1797-2002 (1994-2002)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia, Capitol Model Project Records, 1797-2002 (1994-2002)
The Library of Virginia
39668
1.75 cu. ft.
Library of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Library of Virginia, Special Collections Branch, 24 June 2002.
Biographical Information
Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826), after commissioning Charles-Louis Clerisseau (1721-1820) to execute finished drawings of his design for the Virginia State Capitol, hired Jean-Pierre Fouquet (1752-1829) to create a plaster of paris model to be sent to Virginia. The model was intended to be an aid to workmen at the building site.
Following its use as an instructional tool, the model became a historical artifact displayed for the majority of the 19th century in the Executive Mansion. In the 20th century, it was moved to the Rotunda in the newly expanded Capitol building. Because the model received regular additions of paint over the decades, many of the details were lost and there was a pronounced crackling on the surface.
In 1994, the Library of Virginia, in cooperation with Colonial Williamsburg Foundation and others, undertook an extensive analysis of the Fouquet model resulting in the thorough restoration and conservation of the original and the construction of a replica. The project revealed previously unknown information about the historic paint schemes of the Capitol, the 18th century model building process, and the history of the model itself. Ultimately, the project team decided that only limited restoration could be done to the original building model, so in order to illustrate the fine detail encapsulated under layers of paint, the group commissioned a replica. The reproduction was created using three-dimensional computer models attained from X-rays of the original.
Both Fouquet's original model and the replica will be displayed in the Virginia Capitol in 2007, following its extensive renovation and expansion.
Scope and Content
This accession consists of textual and other materials related to the conservation and reproduction of the 18th century model for the Virginia State Capitol building executed by Jean-Pierre Fouquet for Thomas Jefferson.
These records consist of correspondence, reports, drawings, radiographs, photographs, slides, paint and materials samples. The bulk is made up of a multi-section report detailing the procedures and results of this project. The raw materials that went into creating the final report are also included and consist of radiographic X-rays of the original model, written and photographic analysis of paint and materials samples, photographs of the model at various stages of restoration, and historical images of the Capitol Building. Also included are inkjet reproductions of drawings for the Maison Carree, Jefferson's inspiration for the Virginia Capitol and measured drawings for a new display case for the restored model and its reproduction.
Some oversize materials have been separated and appropriate notations have been made in the contents list below. Two small boxes containing individually-bagged samples (paint and materials) from the Capitol and other Fouquet models are housed inside Box 2. Extreme care should be used when handling these materials.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Conservation, Side Elevation Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Conservation, Side Elevation Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Conservation, Side Elevation Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Conservation, Side Elevation Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Conservation, Side Elevation Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Conservation, Portico Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Conservation, Portico Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Conservation, Base Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Conservation, Rear Facade Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Conservation, Rear Facade Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Conservation, Rear Facade Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Conservation, SEM and EDX Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Conservation, SEM and EDX Samples Data, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Label (19th Century), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Maison Carree Inkjet Prints, ca. 2001, 10 sheets. (Map-case 4/G/3/6, Folder 1)
- Measured Drawings of Pedestal/Vitrine Case with Electro-Magnetic Lifters, 2001, 4 sheets (Map-case 4/G/3/6, Folder 2)
  Drawings for exhibit case to display restored model.
- Microscope Photography Log Sheet and Negatives, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Microscope Photography Log Sheet and Negatives, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Project Report, Section 1-1.3.2, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Project Report, Section 1.3.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Project Report, Section 2-4.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Project Report, Section 5-5.8, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Project Report, Section 6.1-6.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Project Report, Section 7-7.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Project Report, Section 7.4, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Project Report, Section 8.1-8.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Project Report, Section 9.1.1-9.1.3, 1966-2002 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Project Report, Section 9.2-9.2.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Project Report, Section 9.2.4-9.2.7, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  See Box 3 for Oversize separation.
- Project Report, Section 10.1-10.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Project Report, Section 11-12.2, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Project Report, Section 12.2, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Project Report, Section 12.3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Project Report, Section 13-14, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Project Report, Appendix 1, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Project Report, Appendix 2, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Project Report, Appendix 3, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Photographs, ca. 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs, CD-Roms, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs, Negatives, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Radiographs, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Radiographs, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Radiographs, CD-Roms, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Radiographs, Large Format, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  OVERSIZE
- Slides, Historical Images, 1797-1865 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Slides, Model, 1994-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Samples, Paint Cross-Section, ca. 2001 (Box 2, Othertype 1)
  Individual bagged samples housed in a small box.
- Sample, Microscope Slides and Samples from Other Fouquet models, ca. 2001 (Box 2, Othertype 2)
  Individually bagged samples from other Fouquet models and microscope slides of samples from Capitol model.
- Slides, Model (Hanz Lorenz), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)